Julian E. Levi
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Julian E. Levi papers
1846-1981
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Levi, Julian E.
6.6 linear feet
The papers of painter and teacher Julian E. (Edwin) Levi date from 1846 to 1981, and comprise 6.6 linear feet. They include biographical information and extensive correspondence with museums and galleries, as well as letters written to his family, circa 1927, while Levi was living in Paris. Also found within the papers are scattered drawings and sketches by Levi, writings and notes, financial records, two scrapbooks, printed material, miscellaneous records and photographs that document Levi’s professional career and personal life.
Biographical Note
Julian Edwin Levi was born in New York in 1900, and his family relocated to Philadelphia six years later. At age 17, Levi enrolled in the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts where he studied under Henry McCarter and Arthur B. Carles. Upon completing his studies at the Academy in 1919, Levi was awarded one of the Pennsylvania Academy's Cresson Traveling Scholarship which enabled him to travel to Italy during the summer of 1920.
Levi then headed to Paris where he spent the next four years. During this time he became fluent in French, looked at a wide variety of art that influenced him to experiment with abstraction, and had paintings accepted for exhibition the Salon d'Automne of 1921 and 1922. He met many artists in Paris, and developed a close friendship with Jules Pascin. He retuned for a second stay in Paris during 1926 and 1927.
Upon his return to Philadelphia in 1924, Levi and several other modern artists in the city (including his former instructors Carles and McCarter) began exhibiting together under the name "31." The group's work was not well-received. For the remainder of his time in Philadelphia, he continued to paint and on several occasions was able to see Albert Barnes' collection that normally was not open to the public. Levi moved to New York City in 1932 and was attracted to the support and cooperation offered by various artists' organizations. He became a member of An American Group, Inc., in 1933, and was in active in the American Artists' Congress beginning around 1937. Later, Levi was elected to the National Institute of Arts and Letters, an Associate Artist of the National Academy of Design, and a member of the Century Association.
The sea, beaches, dunes, and shores served as inspiration for many of Levi's paintings. He studied his subjects closely, amassing a wide knowledge of boats, fishing, and related equipment; he even learned professional fishing and sailing techniques in order to better understand his subjects. Levi also focused on painting people, and his wife often served as his model. Paintings by Levi are in many museums, among them: Albright-Knox Art Gallery, Art Institute of Chicago, Butler Institute of American Art, Cranbrook Academy of Art, Des Moines Art Center, Detroit Institute of Arts, Guild Hall, Museum of Modern Art, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Newark Museum, Norton Simon Museum, Santa Barbara Museum, Springfield Museum of Art, Toledo Museum, University of Illinois, and the Whitney Museum of American Art.
Many of the paintings Levi produced while employed by the Federal Art Project, 1936-1938, served as the nucleus of his first one-man show held in 1940 at Downtown Gallery. He remained with Downtown Gallery for more than a decade. Later, he was associated with the Alan Gallery, Frank K. M. Rehn Galleries, and Nordness Gallery, each of which staged frequent solo exhibitions of Levi's work. He participated in most of the major national exhibitions and in the Venice Biennale, winning prizes awarded by the Art Institute of Chicago, Carnegie Institute, National Academy of Design, University of Illinois, Guild Hall, and the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts. A large retrospective exhibition of his work was organized by Boston University in 1962, and a small retrospective was held in 1971 at Wake Forest University, Winston-Salem, North Carolina.
A highly respected and much loved teacher, Levi emphasized the importance of drawing and provided individualized instruction. He considered himself a "coach" and viewed his students as less experienced artists (all were encouraged to call him Julian instead of Mr. Levi). His teaching career, which lasted for more than three decades, began in 1946 with his appointments as a painting instructor at the Art Students League and the New School for Social Research in New York City (later the New School appointed him director of its Art Workshop). In 1964 he began making weekly trips to the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts in Philadelphia, where he taught painting; at the start of the 1977 academic year, he reduced his schedule to once a month and acted as a general critic. During the 1967-68 academic year, Levi was on sabbatical leave while artist-in-residence at the American Academy in Rome. In addition, he taught summer courses at Columbia University in the early 1950s and occasionally served as a guest instructor at other summer programs over the years.
Julian Levi died in New York City, February 28, 1982, after a brief illness.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter and teacher Julian E. Levi date from 1846 to 1981, and comprise 6.6 linear feet. They consist of biographical information, correspondence, artwork, writings and notes, financial records, scrapbooks, printed material, miscellaneous records and photographs that document Levi's professional career and personal life.
Biographical information includes French documents regarding his trips to Paris in 1920 and 1926-1927. Julian E. Levi's Correspondence, 1914-1981, and undated, concerns professional and personal matters and consists primarily of incoming letters from friends and colleagues, arts organizations, museums, schools, and galleries. Also found are approximately sixty letters he wrote to his family circa 1927, while living in Paris. In addition, a small number of Henderson Family letters, 1846-1886, are included with the Julian E. Levi papers; their relationship to Levi is unclear. Found within the correspondence are illustrated letters and original artwork in the form of greeting cards. Additional Artwork consists mainly of pencil drawings and sketches by Levi, including a large number of stage costume designs.
Writings by Levi consist of brief statements concerning his work and other artists, brief reminiscences of friends, a poem, and the text of a speech. Notes contain miscellaneous jottings, lists of paintings, addresses and telephone information, and address books. Among the writings by others are catalog introductions for Levi exhibitions by unknown authors, and by Lewis Mumford and Archibald MacLeish for An American Group, Inc.
Financial Records concern both business and personal transactions and document art sales, commissions, consignments, and gallery expenses. Also included are receipts, a small number of banking and tax records, and scattered documentation of purchases, appraisals, and sales of antiques in his collection.
Scrapbooks (2 disbound volumes) contain clippings, other printed items, and a few photographs documenting Levi's exhibitions. There are a substantial number of exhibition catalogs and announcements. Miscellaneous printed material includes brochures, newsletters and publications, clippings, invitations, announcements of meetings, blank postcards, travel brochures and printed souvenirs. Also found is a copy of his book, Modern Art: An Introduction, and one of the articles he published in the American expatriate periodical Gargoyle.
Items of note among the Miscellaneous Records pertain to the American Artists' Congress, An American Group, Inc., Downtown Gallery, and New York City Council for Art Week. Other items of interest are a blueprint of plans for Levi's studio at his home in Easthampton, New York, and records regarding the New School for Social Research where Levi taught for many years.
Photographs of artwork include a disbound album of Levi's work and exhibition installation views that show paintings by Levi. Pictures of Levi include some taken when he was a young child, along with many views of him in his studio, with students, and others. Many views of places probably were used as reference for paintings. Other places recorded in photographs include Downtown Gallery, Stuart Davis's grave, and studios he occupied while in Paris, circa 1926-1927 and at the American Academy in Rome, 1967-1968. Of particular note are copies of Resettlement Administration and Farm Security Administration photographs.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 9 series. Correspondence and Scrapbooks are arranged chronologically. Other series are further categorized by record type or broad topic, with material in each folder arranged chronologically or alphabetically, as noted in the series descriptions.
Series 1: Biographical Information, circa 1906-1980 (Box 1; 14 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1846-1981 (Boxes 1-3, OV 9; 2.3 linear ft.)
Series 3: Artwork, circa 1922-1972 (Box 3; 8 folders)
Series 4: Writings and Notes, circa 1938-1978 (Box 3; 11 folders)
Series 5: Financial Records, 1920s-1980 (Box 3; 0.4 linear ft.)
Series 6: Scrapbooks, 1921-1940(Box 4; 2 folders)
Series 7: Printed Material, circa 1922-1981(Boxes 4-6 and OV 10; 2.3 linear ft.)
Series 8: Miscellaneous Records, circa 1940-1974 (Box 6 and OV 9; 0.2 linear ft.)
Series 9: Photographs, circa 1902-1974 (Boxes 6-8 and OV 11; 1.1 linear ft.)
Index of Selected Correspondents
Included among Julian Levi's correspondence (Series 2) with museums and galleries, art schools, art organizations, artists, and friends and colleagues are the following correspondents.
Abbott, Berenice (1929-1930)
Alan Gallery (1955)
American Academy in Rome (1948-1949, 1958-1960, 1962-1963, 1967-1971)
American Artists' Congress (1937, 1940-1941, undated)
American Federation of Arts (1940, 1942-1944, 1953)
An American Group, Inc. (1933-1934, 1937, 1939-1941, 1947, 1950-1951, undated)
Arms, John Taylor (1946, 1949)
Art Institute of Chicago (1934, 1937-1938, 1940-1941, 1943)
Art Students' League (1948-1949, 1954, 1957-1958, 1960, 1962, 1964-1966, 1968-1970, 1972, 1977-1978, 1981, undated)
Associated American Artists (1941, 1943-1945, 1966, 1972)
Baskin, Leonard (1952, 1962)
Bearden, Romare (1974)
Biddle, George (1969, undated)
Blitzstein, Marc (1928, 1930, 1934)
Blume, Peter and Ebie (1935-1938, 1940, 1949, 1958-1960, 1962, 1967, 1971, undated)
Borie, Adolphe (1927)
Boulevard (see: Moss, Arthur)
Calder, Alexander (1941, 1943, 1945, 1962)
Carnegie Institute (1940-1941, 1943-1950)
Century Association (1963-1967, 1970-1973, 1978-1981)
Coates, Robert (1927, 1937, 1941, 1949, 1951-1953, 1955, 1966, 1969, undated)
Cohen, Lewis and Norma (1969-1971, 1974)
Corcoran Gallery of Art (1941, 1945-1948, 1951, 1963, undated)
Crawford, Ralston and Peggy (1965, 1967, 1969-1970, 1978)
Crillon Galleries, Inc. (1933)
Davidson, Jo (1944)
Davis, Stuart and Roselle (1937, 1939, 1941-1943, 1946, 1953, 1961-1962, 1965, 1968)
Downtown Gallery/Edith Gregor Halpert (1939-1947, 1949, 1951-1955, 1957-1960, 1963)
Duchamp, Marcel (1960)
East River Gallery (1937-1939)
Evergood, Philip (1961-1962, 1964)
Ferguson, Robert (1949, 1952-1953, 1957, 1962)
Fiene, Ernest (1947)
Force, Juliana (see: Whitney Museum of American Art)
Ford Foundation (1958-1959, 1964, 1966-1967)
Frankenstein, Alfred V. (1947-1948, undated)
Gargoyle (see: Moss, Arthur)
Grattan, C. Hartley (1937-1938, 1940, 1942-1943, 1945-1946, 1951-1952, 1965, 1967, 1969, 1970-1973, 1977, undated)
Grosz, George (1922)
Gross, Chaim (1964)
Guerrero, Jose and Roxane (1966-1967)
Guild Hall (1949, 1952-1954, 1957-1962, 1964, 1966-1970, 1972, 1978, undated)
Guston, Philip (1946)
Gwathmey, Robert (1966, undated)
Halpert, Edith G. (see: Downtown Gallery)
Harari, Hananiah (1974)
Helión, Jean (1968)
Hiler, Hilaire (1922)
Hirsch, Joseph (1950, 1967, 1973, 1980, undated)
John Becker Modern Paintings and Facsimiles (1933, undated)
Kelly, Leon and Elizabeth (1927-1931, 1933, 1941, 1949, 1955, 1965-1966, undated)
Kelly, Patricia (1974-1975, 1977-1978, 1980-1981)
Kroll, Leon (1944, 1955)
Kuniyoshi, Isamu and Sara (1936-1937, 1941, 1945, 1951, 1979, undated)
Lauck, Anthony J. (1948-1949, 1953, 1959, 1964-1967, 1970, 1972, 1974, 1981)
Lawrence, Jacob (1970, undated)
Manso, Leo (1974, 1976, 1978-1979, 1981, undated)
Marin, John and Norma (1954, 1964)
Mathieu, Marion (1975, 1981)
McCarter, Henry (undated)
McCausland, Elizabeth (1945)
Metroplitan Museum of Art (1941, 1965)
Milmoe, Dolores (1973, 1977-1981)
Mitchell, Bruce (1956)
Morris, George L. K. (1965)
Moss, Arthur/Boulevard/Gargoyle (1922-1923, 1930)
Mumford, Lewis and Sophia (1937, 1939)
Munce, Howard (1947, 1976-1977, 1980)
Museum of Modern Art (1940-1945, 1954-1955, 1960, 1964, undated)
National Academy of Design (1945-1946, 1949, 1952-1953, 1956-1957, 1970, 1972, 1974-1978, 1980-1981, undated)
National Institute of Arts and Letters (1944, 1955, 1959-1961, 1963-1965, 1967-1975)
New School for Social Research (1954, 1958-1959, 1961-1972, 1975, 1977, 1979, undated)
New York World's Fair (1938-1939)
Newman, Arnold (1943, 1945)
Nivola, Constantino (1970-1971, 1980, undated)
Nordness Gallery (1957-1966, undated)
Pascin, Jules (undated)
Pearson, Ralph M. (1940)
Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts (1916, 1927, 1929, 1939, 1943-1944, 1946, 1952, 1955, 1958, 1961-1963, 1965, 1966-1979)
Pittman, Hobson (undated)
Prestopino, Gregorio (1960, 1962-1963, 1965, 1967-1969, undated)
Prohaska, Ray (1970-1971, 1980)
Public Works of Art Project (1934, undated)
Quirt, Walter (1940)
Rattner, Abraham (1969, undated)
Ray, Man (1928-1929)
Rehn Gallery (1966)
Reiss, Lionel S. (1940)
Robinson, Ione (1936-1938)
Sabatini, Raphael (1973, 1976)
Speight, Francis (1936, 1966, 1969, 1976, undated)
Telemaque, Herve (1960-1961, 1966, 1971, undated)
Treasury Department, Section of Fine Arts (1943)
United American Artists (1940-1941)
Watkins, Franklin C. and Ida (1926, 1937, 1941, 1964-1965, 1969, undated)
Weber, Max (1939, 1942, 1949)
Whitney Museum of American Art/Juliana Force (1935, 1937-1938, 1940-1942, 1944-1945, 1953, 1974)
Works Progress Administration (1936-1937, 1939-1940)
Wright, Russell (1940-1941)
Zorach, William (1943)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.
Subjects:
Downtown Gallery (New York, N.Y.); New School for Social Research (New York, N.Y.) -- Faculty; An American Group (Organization); American Artists' Congress
Subjects-Topical:
Painting, Modern -- 20th century -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters; Artists' studios; Art -- Economic aspects; Art -- Study and teaching
Types of Materials:
Works of art -- local; Interviews; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Illustrated letters -- Local; Drawings; Sketches
Provenance
The papers were a gift received in several accessions between 1969-1982 from Julian E. Levi and his estate (Herman Englander, executor). Portions of the collection were microfilmed upon receipt.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment and is limited to the Washington, D.C. office.
Alternative Forms Available
Portions of the collection are available on microfilm reels 483-486 and 3244-3248 at AAA offices and through interlibrary loan. The current arrangement of the collection does not match the filmed arrangement.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Information, circa 1906-1980, Series 1:; (Box 1; 14 folders)
  This series is arranged into 2 subseries:
  1.1: Julian E. Levi, 1906-1980, undated
  1.2: Jean Laurent Levi (wife), 1949-1980
  - Julian E. Levi, 1906-1980, undated, 1.1:
    - Automobile Registration and Drivers' License, 1932-1973 (Box 1)
    - Awards and Certificates, 1919-1980 (Box 1)
    - Biographical Notes, circa 1933-circa 1975 (Box 1)
    - Draft Registration and Notices of Classification Status, 1918, 1942-1945, undated (Box 1)
    - Educational Records, 1914-1920 (Box 1)
    - Exhibitor's Tickets, 1939-1942 (Box 1)
    - French Identity Card, Admissions Cards, and Legal Summons, 1920-1927 (Box 1)
    - Marriage Certificate and Divorce Papers (first wife, Beatrice Graitcer), 1930-1935 (Box 1)
    - Membership Cards (A-Z, by organization), 1924-1973 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Items, 1906-1947 (Box 1)
    - Passports, 1920-1971 (Box 1)
  - Jean Laurent Levi, 1949-1980, 1.2:
    - Dog Obedience Training (course information, rosters, and certificates), 1952 (Box 1)
    - Membership Cards, 1949-1980 (Box 1)
    - Passports, 1965-1971 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, circa 1846-1981, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-3, OV 9; 2.3 linear ft.)
  Julian E. Levi's correspondence, 1914-1981, and undated, concerns professional and personal matters. It consists primarily of incoming letters (a few of which are addressed to his wife, Jean Laurent Levi) with a small number of drafts and carbon copies of letters written by Levi. There are a number of illustrated letters and greeting cards (primarily Christmas cards) with original artwork by Levi and others. Among his correspondents are museums and galleries including: Alan Gallery, Carnegie Institute, Corcoran Gallery of Art, Downtown Gallery and Edith Halpert, Guild Hall, National Academy of Design, Lee Nordness Gallery, Frank K. M. Rehn Inc., Whitney Museum of American Art and Juliana Force; the art schools where he taught: Art Students' League, New School for Social Research, and Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts; art organizations such as: the American Academy in Rome, American Artists' Congress, An American Group, Inc., National Institute of Arts and Letters, and United American Artists; and friends and colleagues including: Leonard Baskin, George Biddle, Marc Blitzstein, Peter and Ebie Blume, Louis Bouché, Robert Coates, Ralston Crawford, Stuart and Roselle Davis, Marcel Duchamp, Philip Evergood, Alfred Frankenstein, C. Hartley Grattan, Hilaire Hiler, Joseph Hirsch, Leon Kelly, Patricia Kelly, Yasuo and Sara Kuniyoshi, Anthony Lauck, Jacob Lawrence, Dolores Milmoe, Arthur Moss, Gregorio Prestopino, Walter Quirt, Abraham Rattner, Man Ray, Ione Robinson, Francis Speight, Hervé Télémaque, Franklin C. and Ida Watkins, Max Weber, and Russell Wright.
  Approximately 60 letters Levi wrote to his family from Paris circa 1927, survive. They comment on the activities of Franklin Watkins, Marc Blitzstein, and Hilaire Hiler; his own paintings and commissions, particularly for the nightclub, Chez Mister Finney; and his associations with other artists and writers including Ludwig Lewisohn, Roy Sheldon, Maruice Speiser, collector Otto Kahn, and Ford Madox Ford.
  The Julian Levi Papers contain Henderson family letters, 1846-1886, that consist of a letter from S.N.B. Henderson of Covington, Ind. to her parents, Dr. and Mrs. J. L. Richmond, Indianapolis, Ind.; and postcards from Mrs. A. Henderson to her children in Lafayette, Ind. The relationship to Levi is unclear.
  An Index of selected correspondents, provides a more comprehensive list of Julian Levi's correspondence.
  Additional correspondence, 1938-1939, concerning the Estate of Rosa Gomprecht (Julian Levi was a beneficiary) is filed with Financial Records (Series 5).
  2.1: Julian E. Levi, circa 1914-1981, undated
  2.2: Henderson Family Letters, 1846-1886
  - Julian E. Levi, 1914-1981, undated, 2.1:
    - Correspondence, 1914- 1926 (Box 1)
    - Letters to his Family from Paris, circa 1927 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1927-1961, (30 folders) (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1962-1981, (26 folders) (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, undated, (alphabetical; See also: OV 9; 8 folders) (Box 3)
    - Oversize Correspondence (2 illustrated letters from Levi to his wife Valentine and Washington's Birthday, water colors; and Bon Voyage Card - calligraphy - from Students), undated (Box OV 9)
  - Henderson Family Letters, 1846-1886, 2.2:
    - Letters, 1846-1886 (Box 3)
- Artwork, circa 1922-1972, Series 3:; (Box 3; 8 folders)
  Artwork by Levi consists of mainly of pencil drawings and sketches. Included are a large number of stage costume designs, some annotated, and a few with fabric samples attached.
  Additional artwork, in the form of illustrated letters and greeting cards by Levi and other artists, is filed with Correspondence (Series 2).
  This series is organized into 2 subseries:
  3.1: By Levi, 1922, 1950, undated
  3.2: By Other Artists, 1942, 1972, undated
  - By Levi, 3.1:
    - Drawings and Sketches, 1922, 1950, undated, (pencil; loose sheets and a small pad with 14 sketches) (Box 3)
    - Drawings of Stage Costumes, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Painting (oil on canvas), undated (Box 3)
    - Sketchbook (pencil sketches and 1 pastel drawing; spiral bound, some loose pages), undated (Box 3)
  - By Other Artists, 1942, 1972, undated, 3.2:
    - Davidson, Lawrence (etching and gouache); Davis, Stuart (silkscreen); Houser, Alonzo (ink painting); Lippert, Margaret (illustrated resumé); and Unknown (pen and ink drawing), 1972, undated (Box 3)
    - Drawings by Children (Tommy Coates and unknown), 1942, undated (Box 3)
    - Monoprint (color), undated (Box 3)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1938-1982, Series 4:; (Box 3; 11 folders)
  Writings by Levi consist of brief statements concerning his work, other artists (possibly recommendations in support of fellowship applications or short introductions to exhibition catalogs), reminiscences (eulogies?) of deceased artist friends, a poem, and the text of a speech. Also included are notes consisting of miscellaneous jottings, lists of paintings, addresses and telephone information, and address books.
  Writings by others include catalog introductions by for Levi exhibitions by unknown authors, and by Lewis Mumford and Archibald MacLeish for An American Group exhibitions. Also included are poems, an article about Gandy Brodie by Meyer Schapiro, and the text of J. Bronowski's Blashfield Address delivered to the American Academy of Arts and Letters.
  Other notes by Levi (in a folder titled "Teaching") and additional items such as artists' statements and various reports are filed with Miscellaneous Records (Series 8).
  4.1: By Levi, circa 1940-1978,
  4.2: By Other Authors, circa 1938-1982
  - By Levi, circa 1940-1978, undated, 4.1
    - Address Books, undated, (2 disbound vols. with loose notes) (Box 3)
    - Addresses and Telephone Numbers, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Layout for Modern Art: An Introduction by Julian Levi, [circa 1961] (Box 3)
    - Lists of Artwork and Photographs of Artwork (with negative numbers), undated (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Box 3)
    - Teaching Notes, undated (Box 3)
    - Writings, circa 1940-1978, undated (Box 3)
  - By Other Authors, 1938-1982, undated, 4.2
    - Writings About Levi, 1961, undated (Box 3)
    - An American Group, Inc. Catalog Introductions (Lewis Mumford and Archibald MacLeish), 1938-1943, undated (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Writings by Others, 1966-1982, undated (Box 3)
- Financial Records, 1920s-1980, Series 5:; (Box 3; 0.4 linear ft.)
  Financial records concern both business and personal transactions. Business records document art sales, commissions, consignments, and related expenses, arranged by gallery. Receipts and invoices record expenditures for art supplies, framing, insurance, photography, shipping, etc. Financial records relating to Levi's personal expenses document his appraisals, purchases, and sales of antiques in his collection, along with banking and investment records, and receipts and invoices for personal and household expenses.
  - Appraisals of Antiques, 1959-circa 1970, undated (Box 3)